<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<elements>
    <info>
        <author>Tanner Caffrey</author>
        <version>1.6</version>
        <date>2024-07-01</date>
        <update version="0.0.6">
            <file name="sorcerer-wretched-bloodline.xml"
                url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/tanner-caffrey/grim/main/sorcerer-wretched/sorcerer-wretched-bloodline.xml" />
        </update>
    </info>
    <element name="Wretched Bloodline" type="Archetype" source="Grim Hollow Players Guide"
        id="ID_GRIM_HOLLOW_ARCHETYPE_WRETCHED_BLOODLINE">
        <supports>Sorcerous Origin</supports>
        <description>
            <p>With every promise made to a fairy, contract signed with a devil, and pact with the
                unquiet dead, there's a chance someone doesn't keep their end of the bargain. The
                vengeance of immortal beings lasts much longer than one lifetime, and the lingering
                magic of these curses can affect the mortal's descendants.</p>
            <p>These inherited magical afflictions may manifest as a plague, deformity, or aversion
                to the sun. In such families, a child may be born that learns to master the latent
                magic within their inherited curse, turning their bloodline's bane into a personal
                boon—these sorcerers are known collectively as the Wretched.</p>
            <div element="ID_GRIM_HOLLOW_FEATURE_BAD_LUCK_CHARM" />
            <div element="ID_GRIM_HOLLOW_FEATURE_BLOOD_TIES" />
            <div element="ID_GRIM_HOLLOW_FEATURE_WRETCHED_CURSE" />
            <div element="ID_GRIM_HOLLOW_FEATURE_SHARE_THE_BURDEN" />
            <div element="ID_GRIM_HOLLOW_FEATURE_TERRIFYING_VISAGE" />
            <div element="ID_GRIM_HOLLOW_FEATURE_VENGEFUL_SUMMONS" />
        </description>
        <sheet display="false">
            <description>Your innate magic comes from a curse passed down through your bloodline.</description>
        </sheet>
        <rules>
            <grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_GRIM_HOLLOW_FEATURE_BAD_LUCK_CHARM" level="1" />
            <grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_GRIM_HOLLOW_FEATURE_BLOOD_TIES" level="1" />
            <grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_GRIM_HOLLOW_FEATURE_WRETCHED_CURSE" level="1" />
            <grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_GRIM_HOLLOW_FEATURE_SHARE_THE_BURDEN" level="6" />
            <grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_GRIM_HOLLOW_FEATURE_TERRIFYING_VISAGE" level="14" />
            <grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_GRIM_HOLLOW_FEATURE_VENGEFUL_SUMMONS" level="18" />
        </rules>
    </element>

    <element name="Bad Luck Charm" type="Archetype Feature" source="Grim Hollow Players Guide"
        id="ID_GRIM_HOLLOW_FEATURE_BAD_LUCK_CHARM">
        <supports>Wretched Bloodline</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Starting at 1st level, you have mastered the ability to temporarily cast a small
                fragment of your curse onto another. You can use a bonus action to choose a creature
                you can see within 30 feet. The chosen creature has disadvantage on the next ability
                check, attack roll, or saving throw it makes. Once you use this feature, you can't
                do so again until you finish a short or long rest, unless you spend 1 sorcery point
                to use it again.</p>
        </description>
        <sheet action="Bonus Action" usage="1/Short Rest">
            <description>Choose a creature you can see within 30 feet. It has disadvantage on the
                next ability check, attack roll, or saving throw it makes. You can spend 1 sorcery
                point to use it again.</description>
        </sheet>
    </element>

    <element name="Blood Ties" type="Archetype Feature" source="Grim Hollow Players Guide"
        id="ID_GRIM_HOLLOW_FEATURE_BLOOD_TIES">
        <supports>Wretched Bloodline</supports>
        <description>
            <p>At 1st level, your senses easily attune to the supernatural forces that caused your
                inherited affliction. You know the detect evil and good spell and can cast it
                without expending a spell slot. This spell counts as a sorcerer spell for you but
                does not count against your number of spells known. Once you cast this spell without
                expending a spell slot, you can't do so again until you finish a short or long rest.</p>
            <p>In addition, choose one of the following creature types as the being who cursed your
                ancestor: fey, fiend, or undead. While you are concentrating on the detect evil and
                good spell, creatures of the chosen type have disadvantage on attack rolls against
                you, and you cannot be charmed, frightened, or possessed by such creatures.</p>
        </description>
        <sheet action="Action" usage="1/Short Rest">
            <description>You know the detect evil and good spell and can cast it without expending a
                spell slot once per short or long rest.</description>
        </sheet>
        <rules>
            <grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_DETECT_EVIL_AND_GOOD" known="true" />
            <select type="Archetype Feature" name="Blood Ties Creature Type"
                supports="ID_GRIM_HOLLOW_FEATURE_BLOOD_TIES_FEY|ID_GRIM_HOLLOW_FEATURE_BLOOD_TIES_FIEND|ID_GRIM_HOLLOW_FEATURE_BLOOD_TIES_UNDEAD" />
        </rules>
    </element>

    <element name="Blood Ties (Fey)" type="Archetype Feature" source="Grim Hollow Players Guide"
        id="ID_GRIM_HOLLOW_FEATURE_BLOOD_TIES_FEY">
        <supports>Blood Ties Creature Type</supports>
        <sheet>
            <description>
                While you are concentrating on the detect evil and good spell, Fey creatures have
                disadvantage on attack rolls against you, and you cannot be charmed, frightened, or
                possessed by such creatures.
            </description>
        </sheet>
    </element>

    <element name="Blood Ties (Fiend)" type="Archetype Feature" source="Grim Hollow Players Guide"
        id="ID_GRIM_HOLLOW_FEATURE_BLOOD_TIES_FIEND">
        <supports>Blood Ties Creature Type</supports>
        <sheet>
            <description>
                While you are concentrating on the detect evil and good spell, Fiend creatures have
                disadvantage on attack rolls against you, and you cannot be charmed, frightened, or
                possessed by such creatures.
            </description>
        </sheet>
    </element>

    <element name="Blood Ties (Undead)" type="Archetype Feature" source="Grim Hollow Players Guide"
        id="ID_GRIM_HOLLOW_FEATURE_BLOOD_TIES_UNDEAD">
        <supports>Blood Ties Creature Type</supports>
        <sheet>
            <description>
                While you are concentrating on the detect evil and good spell, Undead creatures have
                disadvantage on attack rolls against you, and you cannot be charmed, frightened, or
                possessed by such creatures.
            </description>
        </sheet>
    </element>

    <element name="Wretched Curse" type="Archetype Feature" source="Grim Hollow Players Guide"
        id="ID_GRIM_HOLLOW_FEATURE_WRETCHED_CURSE">
        <supports>Wretched Bloodline</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Also at 1st level, you suffer from a curse inherited from an ancestor who failed to
                uphold their end of a bargain with an otherworldly power. Choose one of the
                following curses that was passed down to you. Choose one of the following curses
                inherited from an ancestor who failed to
                uphold their end of a bargain with an otherworldly power.</p>
        </description>
        <rules>
            <select type="Archetype Feature" name="Wretched Curse Type"
                supports="ID_GRIM_HOLLOW_FEATURE_HULKING|ID_GRIM_HOLLOW_FEATURE_NOCTURNAL|ID_GRIM_HOLLOW_FEATURE_PLAGUEBEARER" />
        </rules>
    </element>

    <element name="Hulking" type="Archetype Feature" source="Grim Hollow Players Guide"
        id="ID_GRIM_HOLLOW_FEATURE_HULKING">
        <supports>Wretched Curse Type</supports>
        <description>Your ancestor was cursed with a hulking frame. You have disadvantage on
            Dexterity (Stealth) checks made to move quietly. Your max hit points increase by 1 for
            each level in this class. You count as one size larger for carrying capacity and weight
            you can push, drag, or lift.</description>
        <sheet>
            <description>
                Your ancestor was cursed with a hulking frame. You have disadvantage on Dexterity
                (Stealth) checks made to move quietly. Your max hit points increase by 1 for each
                level in this class ({{hulking:hp}}). You count as one size larger for carrying
                capacity and weight
                you can push, drag, or lift.
            </description>
        </sheet>
        <rules>
            <stat name="hulking:hp" value="level" />
            <stat name="hp" value="hulking:hp" />
        </rules>
    </element>

    <element name="Nocturnal" type="Archetype Feature" source="Grim Hollow Players Guide"
        id="ID_GRIM_HOLLOW_FEATURE_NOCTURNAL">
        <supports>Wretched Curse Type</supports>
        <description>Your ancestor was cursed to shun the light of day. You have disadvantage on
            Wisdom (Perception) checks made to see in sunlight. You have darkvision out to 120 feet
            and can see through magical darkness within that range.</description>
        <sheet>
            <description>Your ancestor was cursed to shun the light of day. You have disadvantage on
                Wisdom (Perception) checks made to see in sunlight. You have darkvision out to 120
                feet and can see through magical darkness within that range.</description>
        </sheet>
        <rules>
            <grant type="Vision" id="ID_VISION_SUPERIORDARKVISION" />
        </rules>
    </element>

    <element name="Plaguebearer" type="Archetype Feature" source="Grim Hollow Players Guide"
        id="ID_GRIM_HOLLOW_FEATURE_PLAGUEBEARER">
        <supports>Wretched Curse Type</supports>
        <description>Your ancestor was cursed with physical symptoms of a plague. You have
            disadvantage on Charisma (Persuasion) checks made against humanoid creatures who are not
            blinded. You are immune to disease and have resistance to necrotic damage.</description>
        <sheet>
            <description>Your ancestor was cursed with physical symptoms of a plague. You have
                disadvantage on Charisma (Persuasion) checks made against humanoid creatures who are
                not blinded. You are immune to disease and have resistance to necrotic damage.</description>
        </sheet>
    </element>

    <element name="Share the Burden" type="Archetype Feature" source="Grim Hollow Players Guide"
        id="ID_GRIM_HOLLOW_FEATURE_SHARE_THE_BURDEN">
        <supports>Wretched Bloodline</supports>
        <description>
            <p>At 6th level, you learn the bestow curse spell. This spell counts as a sorcerer spell
                for you, but it doesn't count against your number of sorcerer spells known. When you
                cast the spell, you can choose to cast it by spending 5 sorcery points instead of a
                spell slot. If you cast the spell using sorcery points, its range changes to 60 feet
                for that casting and your concentration can't be broken as a result of taking
                damage.</p>
        </description>
        <sheet action="Action">
            <description>
                When you cast Bestow Curse, you can choose to cast it by spending 5 sorcery points
                instead of a spell slot. If you cast the spell using sorcery points, its range
                changes to 60 feet for that casting and your concentration can't be broken as a
                result of taking damage.
            </description>
        </sheet>
        <rules>
            <grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_BESTOW_CURSE" known="true" />
        </rules>
    </element>
    <element name="Terrifying Visage" type="Archetype Feature" source="Grim Hollow Players Guide"
        id="ID_GRIM_HOLLOW_FEATURE_TERRIFYING_VISAGE">
        <supports>Wretched Bloodline</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Beginning at 14th level, you can use a bonus action to adopt the terrifying visage of
                the being who cursed your ancestor for 10 minutes. During this time, you can use an
                action on each of your turns to cause each creature who can see you within 30 feet
                make a Wisdom saving throw against your sorcerer spell save DC. On a failure, a
                creature is frightened of you until the end of your next turn.</p>
            <p>In addition, while you have adopted the terrifying visage, you gain an additional
                benefit based on the creature type chosen with your Blood Ties feature.</p>
            <p>Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.</p>
        </description>
        <sheet action="Bonus Action" usage="1/Long Rest">
            <description>
                You adopt the terrifying visage of the being who cursed your ancestor for 10
                minutes. During this time, you can use an action on each of your turns to cause each
                creature who can see you within 30 feet make a Wisdom saving throw against your
                sorcerer spell save DC. On a failure, a creature is frightened of you until the end
                of your next turn.
            </description>
        </sheet>
        <rules>
            <select type="Archetype Feature" name="Terrifying Visage Benefit"
                supports="ID_GRIM_HOLLOW_FEATURE_TERRIFYING_VISAGE_FEY|ID_GRIM_HOLLOW_FEATURE_TERRIFYING_VISAGE_FIEND|ID_GRIM_HOLLOW_FEATURE_TERRIFYING_VISAGE_UNDEAD" />
        </rules>
    </element>

    <element name="Terrifying Visage (Fey)" type="Archetype Feature"
        source="Grim Hollow Players Guide" id="ID_GRIM_HOLLOW_FEATURE_TERRIFYING_VISAGE_FEY">
        <supports>Terrifying Visage Benefit</supports>
        <sheet action="Bonus Action">
            <description>
                While you have adpoted the terrifying visage, you may teleport up to 30 feet in any
            direction.
            </description>
            > </sheet>
    </element>

    <element name="Terrifying Visage (Fiend)" type="Archetype Feature"
        source="Grim Hollow Players Guide" id="ID_GRIM_HOLLOW_FEATURE_TERRIFYING_VISAGE_FIEND">
        <supports>Terrifying Visage Benefit</supports>
        <sheet>
            <description>
                While you have adpoted the terrifying visage, you have resistance to cold and fire
            damage.
            </description>
            > </sheet>
    </element>

    <element name="Terrifying Visage (Undead)" type="Archetype Feature"
        source="Grim Hollow Players Guide" id="ID_GRIM_HOLLOW_FEATURE_TERRIFYING_VISAGE_UNDEAD">
        <supports>Terrifying Visage Benefit</supports>
        <sheet action="Reaction" usage="While Terrifying Visage">
            <description>
                While you have adpoted the terrifying visage, when you take damage that isn't
            radiant, you can use your reaction to reduce that damage by an amount equal to half your
            sorceror level.
            </description>
            > </sheet>
    </element>

    <element name="Vengeful Summons" type="Archetype Feature" source="Grim Hollow Players Guide"
        id="ID_GRIM_HOLLOW_FEATURE_VENGEFUL_SUMMONS">
        <supports>Wretched Bloodline</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Beginning at 18th level, your magic has become powerful enough that you can call and
                command a servant of those that cursed you. Choose one of the following creatures as
                a representative for your curse based on the choice you made with your Blood Ties
                feature: lamia or troll (fey only), barbed devil or incubus/succubus (fiend only),
                ghost or wraith (undead only).</p>
            <p>You can use an action and spend 5 sorcery points to summon your chosen creature. The
                creature appears in an unoccupied space you can see within 60 feet, and disappears
                when it drops to 0 hit points, you use this feature to summon another creature, or
                after 10 minutes have passed.</p>
            <p>Roll initiative for the creature, which has its own turns. When you summon it and on
                each of your turns thereafter, you can issue a verbal command to it (requiring no
                action on your part), telling it what it must do on its next turn. If you issue no
                command, it spends its turn attacking any creature within reach.</p>
        </description>
        <sheet>
            <description>
                <p>Beginning at 18th level, your magic has become powerful enough that you can call
                    and
                    command a servant of those that cursed you. Choose one of the following
                    creatures as
                    a representative for your curse based on the choice you made with your Blood
                    Ties
                    feature: lamia or troll (fey only), barbed devil or incubus/succubus (fiend
                    only),
                    ghost or wraith (undead only).</p>
                <p>You can use an action and spend 5 sorcery points to summon your chosen creature.
                    The
                    creature appears in an unoccupied space you can see within 60 feet, and
                    disappears
                    when it drops to 0 hit points, you use this feature to summon another creature,
                    or
                    after 10 minutes have passed.</p>
                <p>Roll initiative for the creature, which has its own turns. When you summon it and
                    on
                    each of your turns thereafter, you can issue a verbal command to it (requiring
                    no
                    action on your part), telling it what it must do on its next turn. If you issue
                    no
                    command, it spends its turn attacking any creature within reach.</p>
            </description>
        </sheet>
        <!-- <select type="Archetype Feature" name="Vengeful Summons Creature"
            supports="Lamia|Troll|Barbed Devil|Incubus|Succubus|Ghost|Wraith" /> -->
    </element>
</elements>